hi everybody my name is Tom Hoot
principal trumpet of the Los Angeles Philharmonic
Today I am
extremely excited to share with you a new invention
a new resource
a new tool for brass players
it's called the ambashore
you know one of the problems with brass
playing is that so much of what's happening to make it
possible to play a brass instrument
is happening in areas we can't see
so I invented the ambusher for myself
to help with areas like stamina
response endurance flexibility
core of sound range
so let's dig in
I'm going to tell you all about this
in the following video
and in case you haven't figured it out yet
the reason it's called ambashure
is not because I'm trying to respell the word
it's because I want to talk about the ambashure
and I want to bring a degree of security
to you and your bras playing
maybe you've heard about balance
maybe some teachers talk to you about
balance in your trumpet playing
this is one elusive word
when it comes to playing a brass instrument
this device will help bring
sensitivity and nuance and awareness
to things like balance
we want to create a healthy read
and I'll explain this later in the video
I created the embosure for several reasons
first of which is my own curiosity
as a developing players still to this day
I want to find
new distinctions of how I can make music more
efficiently and with more fun
secondly was for my students
I want to help them find new distinctions in these same
areas and sometimes
giving them the same
sensation that I feel can be a real challenge
so this tool is going to help them with that
and thirdly as a young player
I really had serious limitations to what I could do
and it was really frustrating
things like range and endurance and power
stamina flexibility color core of sound
consistency from day to day
my days felt up and down and up and down
and I would try to sometimes plan
my concerts on the days that I felt good
so whether you're a student a beginner
a teacher or a professional
we all want to find
ease in our brass playing
and put the work in the right place
so that
ultimately you have access to making great music
with no limits
so let's get started
the first component that I want to share with you
is the standard visualizer
in your armature it will come assembled like this
you simply unscrew this portion
and now you have a traditional visualizer
which will come with a 7 rim
for beginners and some piccolo work
a 3 for sort of
middle of the road sized mouthpiece
and a 1.5 for those of you that play a slightly bigger
mouthpiece
today we're not going to get into too many details
but I want to bring awareness to what
each component is created
for the visualizer will basically help
bring awareness to what's happening inside the
rim from a visual standpoint
in later videos I will talk about what to look for
what to look out for and what to aim for
the second component
I want to share with you is the aperture setter
the aperture setter goes inside your visualizer
a nice firm tightening here
the point of the aperture setter
is to bring focus and sensitivity to your read
as a brass player
the reason that I created the aperture setter
is to help balance out the first tool
for years I used the visualizer
but only to find out that it got me spread
and with a big diffuse sound
the aperture setter
is a prerequisite for using the visualizer
and the third part of the ambashore
is the conditioning and coordination tool
now what do I mean by that
you know in trumpa playing and brass playing
there's a lot of fairly simple things to do
the problem is we have to do them all at the same time
if I ask you to blow an Airstream that's simple
if I ask you to
form an ambusher that's fairly simple
move your fingers a certain way
the problem is we have to do all these
things at the same time
the conditioning and coordination tool
helps us do two things at the same time
these two things are
engaging the Embousure
and blowing with a free relaxed Airstream
here we are talking about balance again
but the conditioning and coordination tool will help us
engage the Embousure while blowing at the same time
ultimately I invented the ambashore
to go against an idea
that has been
pervasive in the brass community for years
and this is don't think about your chops
well what if I told an OBO player
don't think about your reads
they would laugh me off the stage
of course
OBO players spend about half of their time creating
optimal beautiful reads
if they know what they sound like
even from a squawk
they can identify
good qualities or bad qualities within a read
ultimately my goal of the ambashure
is to have it be a resource or tool to
bring sensitivity
to how the sound actually happens
okay so let's recap the ambashure
we've got the visualizer with three different rims
we've got the aperture setter
and the coordination and conditioning tool
here in this video
you might be wondering
how do I use these things
don't worry subscribe to my YouTube channel
I have many tutorials that go in specific details
and I'll do the exercise with you
I've created a bunch of backing tracks that will help
you find what's the most natural setup
and work from there
so thanks for watching
I hope you're as excited about this as I am
it's a game changer for me in my own playing
and I hope it will be for you too